I have built two AI agent
chatbots, now I will give the same
prompt to both of them and see which
agent works better for us.
In both the prompts, the same prompt
is to plan a 5 day trip across
Hyderabad, Bangalore, Chennai,
Mysore and Pondicherry.
I want weather and the top
attractions for each city.
What should the agent do for all of
these 5 locations?
On the right side, we already got
the answer and it took approximately
under 18 seconds to solve this
question.
But our left side agent is still
searching for these details,
weather information and attraction
details and it is still trying to
process your answer.
We got the answer as well.
In both the prompts, the answer is
almost the same.
Hyderabad, Bangalore, Chennai,
Mysore and Pondicherry.
But the left side agent took 40
seconds.
Almost 3 times difference.
2.5 to 3 times.
So both the chatbots, same prompt,
same model, almost same code.
But why 2.5 times difference in the
output?
Between these two, there is one
small change in the backend code,
which is we have utilized async IO
programming in the right side agent.
In the left side agent,
we didn't do any async IO
programming.
That's why it is running
sequentially and it is taking too
much time.
So in the next 15 minutes,
I am going to teach you everything
you need to learn regarding async IO
while building AI agents.
Before we start this video,
let's look at the part in our
agentic roadmap.
So in phase 1, 1.8 async
programming, we are going to learn
all of these topics in this video.
So to build AI agents,
in production level, we have
multiple frameworks.
LangChain, AWS Strands,
CrewAI and all of these frameworks
use async IO internally.
So see here, does LangChain use
async programming?
Yes.
And if you look at these Amazon
Strands, yes, they use extensively.
And then CrewAI, yes,
they use it extensively.
Now, if the frameworks used to build
AI agents are dependent on async
IO, we should also know how it
works.
And that is what exactly we are
going to learn even with analogy.
So let's assume we have a chaff.
So what does the chaff do?
He needs to cook biryani,
sambar and curry.
But the chaff has only one burner
stove.
So what does he do first?
He will cook biryani for 2 minutes,
let's assume.
And after that, he will cook sambar
for 2 more minutes.
And after that, he will cook curry
He does all of these in sequence.
So the total time taken is
approximately 6 minutes.
Now there is another chaff.
What is this chaff?
He has 3 burner stoves.
Now he has 3 orders. Biryani,
sambar and curry.
Now what does this chaff do?
He puts 3 different items on 3
burners and prepares everything in 2
minutes.
Now here, in both the parts,
the chaff is the same,
the items are the same.
But the way that he is preparing the
content is different, right?
That is what we call it as a
synchronous, which is happening in a
sequential manner.
And if it is happening in a parallel
manner, that is what we call it as
asynchronous.
Python has shortcut names for this.
It is called sync and async.
So in total, same recipe,
same output, but different waiting
times.
Now let's map this analogy we have
to technical words.
We have chaff, right?
That is what we call it as an AI
agent.
And after that, we have dishes like
sambar, biryani.
That is what we call API calls.
And what does a sync agent do?
One API call calls one time.
What does an asynchronous agent do?
It calls multiple API calls in
parallel.
So that is the whole idea of
synchronous and asynchronous
programming in Python.
It is a very simple concept.
Now what we are going to do is,
let's map this same analogy with the
chartboards that we built.
So what did the first chartbot do?
It is a synchronous chartbot.
Just like our first chartbot.
So let's assume there are 5
different cities in Paris, Tokyo,
New York, London, and Mumbai.
So what does this chartbot do?
First, it goes to Paris for weather
information and attractions.
After that, it goes to Tokyo for
weather attractions.
After that, it goes to New York for
It does two API calls for each
location.
And after each API call ends,
it goes to the next API call.
So in total, it does 10 API calls.
And every API call is taking
approximately 2 seconds.
It wasted 20 seconds there itself.
After that, it goes to the next API
call and summarizes the output.
That took approximately 10 seconds.
So on an average, it is taking
30 seconds to answer a simple
prompt.
What if that is asynchronous code?
So it calls multiple locations,
multiple weathers, multiple
attractions in parallel.
Not in a sequential manner.
And every parallel call ends in
under 2 seconds.
So even if it does 10 API calls,
if everything is done in parallel,
all of them will get completed by 2
seconds.
And after that, another LLM has to
come and summarize, right?
And that summarization is going to
stay same for both of these APIs.
So 10 seconds is 10 seconds.
But if it is done in parallel,
our right asynchronous agent takes
an average of 12 seconds.
Our left synchronous agent is taking
30 seconds for the same solution.
So in this manner, if you are doing
multiple hundreds and thousands of
API calls per day,
it is going to waste a lot of time,
right?
And it is also causing bad user
experience.
Right?
You gave a question with a prompt.
And it took a lot of time to
respond.
What do you think is going to happen
in the next few months?
So this is the whole concept
regarding sync and desync.
In short, if you do it sequentially,
that is called synchronous
programming.
If you do it in parallel,
that is called asynchronous
programming.
All the topics we have learned so
far, let's try to convert that into
Python code.
I have created an IPYNB notebook
here.
I will put the code in the
description below.
You can go and access all the code
base completely.
And you can practice on your own as
well.
So what we are going to learn from
this is,
Async IO in Python is a detailed
practical tutorial.
What is async programming?
What is the difference between async
and async?
How to create?
What is await?
What is asyncio.gather?
What is create task?
And you can learn the remaining
topics from yourself.
What is async IO?
Async IO is an inbuilt library in
Python.
You don't have to install it
separately for writing concurrent
programs.
This is usually used for API calls,
database queries, file downloads,
web scraping, LLM tools,
network services.
And it is not the same as parallel
processing or multi -threading in
Python.
That is a different topic.
We will not talk about those in this
video.
So this is not multi -threading.
So we will not use this for machine
learning training or image
processing.
So let's start with basic Python
functions.
We also call this as subroutines.
So what are we doing here?
I am creating a function which is
called fetchWeather.
And I am printing which city we are
fetching the weather.
And then I am putting a time sleep
of 2 seconds.
And I am returning.
We have done it to this city.
Simple.
And created a list of Paris,
London and Berlin.
And we have started the time.
And for each city, I am calling this
function and I am getting the
output.
Let's execute this code.
And see.
Fetching weather for Paris.
What will happen here?
So whenever we start this loop.
Here first it will come to this
point.
By saying fetchWeather.
It will go here.
After going here, it will print
this.
So we got the print here.
And after that, it will wait for 2
seconds.
And the code will be there for those
2 seconds.
After those 2 seconds are over.
Then we print this.
That is what we are printing result.
And after that, it will go to London
in the loop.
Second time.
And when London comes.
Then we are calling the fetchWeather
again.
For London.
Then London will print.
After that, it will wait for 2
seconds.
And it will print the London again.
So what will happen?
Every time when we are executing the
same function in the loop.
We are waiting there until that loop
gets completed.
Isn't it?
That is how a normal Python will
start executing.
But what should we do to make it
faster?
That is where we have async version.
I will show you the code.
But I will not explain it right now.
Because we will learn in the next
part.
The same piece of code almost.
But when I execute this.
These 3 prints came at the same
time.
And these 3 outputs came at the same
That means 3 function calls happened
at the same time.
Even though we are running in the
loop.
So why did it happen?
Because we have something called as
async.
So whenever we are writing functions
using async.
Whatever we call it.
We will call it as coroutines.
How do we define async functions?
So what we are going to do is.
Let's try to see how to write a
normal function in Python.
So define and put the keyword.
And say hello and put.
Our function is returning inside
this.
And we are calling this.
And we are saving the output inside
subroutine object.
And let's execute this.
What will happen is.
When you call this function say
hello.
It will go here.
And after that it will return this.
That return will be stored in this.
And we are getting print.
That's completely normal.
Now how to write async?
Then there is something called as
async keyword.
In Python.
For the same function.
You can put async to the left side.
Simple.
Nothing complex.
Write async.
Define the function same as it is.
And when you write async.
When you call this function.
It will not execute this function.
That is the important stuff.
Then see.
There is async def here.
And I am calling this function.
Otherwise.
Usually.
What will happen if I print when I
am not async?
I should get this output.
Otherwise.
If I execute this now.
I get something called as.
Coroutine object runtime warning.
What it says here is.
Coroutine say hello was never
awaited.
So.
The meaning is.
Whenever you write functions using
async.
Even though when you call the
functions.
The function is not getting
executed.
Until you use a keyword.
Which is called await.
If I have to call this function.
What should I do?
I should say await.
And then call this function.
Say hello.
So.
Whenever I use await.
On an async function.
Then only.
This function will get executed.
So.
What is await?
Pause here.
Until this async operation
completes.
While waiting.
Allow the event loop.
To run other tasks.
So.
What should we do?
Let's try to create one more
function.
Async definition.
And task button.
Say name.
And I am printing.
What is our task name?
And after that.
I am waiting for 2 seconds.
In async IO.
And then.
I am printing.
It is complete.
And return name.
And now.
To call this function.
What should I do?
I need to say await.
Let's execute this.
And see.
Task A started.
Task A completed.
And result.
Task.
Simple.
Until and unless.
You use await.
You cannot execute the async
function.
And then.
Event loop.
The event loop is the engine behind
async IO.
It keeps track of which tasks are
awaiting.
Which tasks are ready to continue.
And which tasks should run next.
So in normal python scripts.
If you want to execute this async IO
code.
You have to say async IO dot run.
Since we are using it in IPYNB.
We can directly say await main.
If you do it in python files.
Always use async IO dot run.
It will not work if you say await
directly.
I just wanted to show you the
difference as well.
What we should do is.
Let's look at how we can use async
IO.
Using sequential manner.
Here we have function.
Async definition.
API call.
It takes the name as a parameter.
And we are printing the function
started.
And after that.
We are waiting for 2 seconds.
And then.
Function finished.
And returning the name.
Simple.
After that.
I have one more async def.
Which is also a coroutine.
What are we doing here?
For the first time.
I am doing await.
What does await do?
It will go here.
And it will call this function.
That means.
It is passing the name as task 1.
So what is happening here?
Task 1 started.
And it will wait for 2 seconds.
And then it will print task 1
finished.
Simple.
After that.
Task 1 is coming to the result.
Once this is done.
Next you are doing await for the
task 2.
And task 2 will execute.
It will finish.
And await for task 3.
Task 3 will execute.
It will finish.
So let's execute and see the output.
See.
Task 1 started.
We waited for 2 seconds.
Task 1 finished.
Task 2 started.
We waited for 2 seconds.
Task 2 finished.
Task 3 started.
We waited for 2 seconds.
Task 3 finished.
And printing task 1, task 2 and task
3.
Simple.
So to complete 3 functions or 3
awaits.
It took us 6 seconds.
Why?
Every await is taking 2 seconds
sleep.
What is happening here?
Even when you are using async.
We are doing sequential processing.
But.
We can do concurrent processing.
That is the magic of await or async.
So why do we need to do sequential
processing?
We can do direct functions as well.
So what we can do here is.
You have something called as asyncio
.gather.
Instead of directly saying await,
await, await.
You can say asyncio.gather.
What is happening here?
You are calling these 3 calls.
API call, API call, API call.
Using task 1, task 2 and task 3.
So here.
All of these 3 function calls.
Happens parallelly at the same time.
So first API call goes to task 1.
And while it is getting sleep.
At the same time task 2 will start.
While it is in the sleep.
At the same time task 3 will start.
And once all of this.
Execution completes.
That output.
It will give you in the list output.
So let's execute and see output.
See task 1, task 2, task 3.
It started parallelly.
And everything ended at the same
time.
And the output we got also came in
the list.
And to execute the same code.
It took only 2 seconds.
It is not happening sequentially.
It is happening in the parallel
processing.
No.
If you want to do it even better.
Or even different way.
Then there is something which is
called as.
Create task.
So what does create task do?
It schedules the coroutines.
To run.
Soon in the event loop.
Now what are we doing?
Let's assume there is a fetch data
code.
Here there is an async def.
Inside this we are printing
something.
And then we are doing a sleep.
And after that we are doing a
return.
And here.
I have one more async def.
Which is called as main.
Inside this.
What I am doing is.
Async IO.
Create task.
So inside this create task.
I am calling this function.
And here 2.
That is what the sleep time is.
I am passing this.
For the sleep time as 2.
And after that.
Async.
Create task.
Here sleep time is 10.
And after that.
Async.
Create task.
We are not calling the functions.
We are creating the task.
Or coroutine objects.
And that coroutine objects.
Or tasks.
We need to have await.
So what are we doing?
Await task 1.
Await task 2.
And await task 3.
So here the important stuff is.
First when you say await task 1.
This will go into task 1.
It will go here.
And it will do a sleep time of 2
seconds.
When that sleep is happening.
Because it is not doing anything.
It will start for the await task 2.
So at the end.
Await task 2 will start.
And time sleep of task 2 is.
10 seconds.
When 10 seconds is happening.
When it is waiting.
It will start task 3.
And it will execute.
So whenever there is.
Something happening in the
background.
When the waiting is happening.
We are not being ideal.
We are creating the other tasks.
So that can be done.
So let's look at the output.
See the mood has started.
But the first output has come.
There is still 8 seconds for the
second output to come.
After that.
It will go to the third one.
That's how it is.
So either you can use gather.
Or create tasks.
What happens with gather.
If you are running multiple.
Coroutines in parallel.
When something happens in between.
When there is an error in between.
Gather is very hard to debug.
And it is not that much preferable.
I usually use create tasks.
So use gather when you have a batch
of.
Independent tasks.
And want all results at the same
time.
And use create task.
When you want manual control.
Over when a task starts.
And when you want to avoid it.
So if there is more.
You can learn a lot of new stuff.
I will share this code with you
guys.
The entire code is in the
description below.
You can directly download it.
And you can make a copy on your
Google collab as well.
And learn the other stuff.
So let's go back to our original
code base.
I told you to create two agents.
So what is the difference between
those two agents.
One uses async.
One doesn't use async.
So there is agent core.py file.
If you look at this.
I am loading my API key.
And after that.
If you see mockweather.
I wrote mockattractions.
But here I am not using any async.io
definitions.
These are normal function
Getweather.
Getattractions.
And I have the same functions in
async.
Async definition.
And async def.
For the getweather and
getattractions.
So there are two types of agents.
I have written two different
functions.
To showcase the difference.
And after that we call tools.
And after that I need to do await.
So if you look at this one.
I am calling those functions.
So that's why.
Our right side agent.
Performs very fast.
Our left side agent.
Performs very slow.
How to write this code.
You will learn all of that in the
upcoming session.
So don't worry.
We are learning all the foundations.
That are needed.
For us to build these agents in the
later parts.
I have written all of this code.
You will be able to write this code.
After a couple of sessions.
Once we start.
And I hope you learned some new
topics.
Because of this video.
And if you like this video.
Please consider subscribing.
And if you know someone who wants to
learn all of these topics.
And agent TKI.
Please share it with them.